So um like in your um well in your
recent essays you've been
[clears throat] mentioning how the
necessity of celibacy
both like practical and categorical.
So um if say somebody
a householder so somebody who doesn't
live in the monastery doesn't live in
the uh environment that's more conducive for
uh environment that's more conducive for
that but wants to actually undertake the
eight precepts undertake the practice of
celibacy in order to develop the right view.
in order to develop the right view.
um [clears throat] what would be the um
some like um practical considerations
for them as to like how to well increase
chances of their success really
>> because obviously in the world out there
there's um everything is about
sensuality, everything is pointing
towards sensuality. So what how how
would a person go about um in that
environment? What would be the necessary
things necessary practical things for
them to do? consider, uphold and so on
so that they can actually
>> um develop [clears throat] those
precepts. >> Thing is one thing that's very commonly
>> Thing is one thing that's very commonly
mentioned in the sutas is that your u
the quality of your friendships has a
very direct impact on the qualities that
you have in your mind. So the people
that you're hanging out with, if those
people have sensual values, even if you
try to cultivate the opposite values, by
default, the current is taking you in
the opposite direction. So you want to
be careful that you're not that you're
minimizing contact with um people who
value sensuality, who would find fault
with you for trying to practice the
dharma. You can't completely sometimes
remove those people from your life. But
if you're actively maintaining
friendships with them, not just like,
oh, I have to talk to him because he's
my coworker or something. You're
actively maintaining relationship with
them and you are,
by that token, you're giving their
opinions. Wait, so it's going to
influence your mind, going to kind of
taint your views with these wrong
emphases. So that's the first thing. And
then secondly, you want to recognize
well even if other people are doing
whatever they might be doing that
doesn't absolve you from your
responsibility. So as there's that suda
where the Buddha said uh others will be
killing here we will not be killing
others will be stealing here we will not
be stealing. So you you certainly
shouldn't expect your environment to be
perfectly conducive that like oh because
everybody around me is is uh going the
same direction that's why I can do it.
More often than not that will not be the
case even in the monastery for that
matter. You will not find uh everyone
being uh 100% on the same page. So you
have to feel that weight of yeah like I
I could do the opposite. I could choose
to give into sensuality. I could choose
to uh be careless, but then I will be
paying the price for that. It's not like
um the weight of tradition or the weight
of uh a group that's making you do it.
If it is, then your determination will
crack as soon as those external factors
are compromised.
>> Mhm.
Uh any other [clears throat]
other practical?
>> Yeah. Well, uh, another thing to keep in
mind is
you might have to, depending on how
proliferated you've been, you might have
to take it gradually. So, you know, when
we talk about um, celibacy is necessary.
You have to completely give some
reality, that's that should be your
value. That should be your goal. But you
want to recognize that if you try to
take that all of a sudden too much all
at once, you might end up um you know
slingshotting back into your old habits
because it was just too much for you to
bear. So you want to keep that as your
goal. You want to feel the inadequacy of
the remaining sensual habits that you
might have. You want to avoid um
shifting the goalpost and trying to
justify them because I'm a lay person.
and it's fine or something. Um but then
at the same time you you want to work
towards it gradually. So if you haven't
been keeping the five precepts then
start with that. If you um have been
keeping the five precepts already then
start building it up. Take more um like
start removing
sensual indulgences that you know are
completely unnecessary and you just give
into them out of weakness. um take on
the eight precepts on occasion like on
the opposite
>> and then [clears throat] uh work towards
making that your permanent mode of being
because it's about seeing
again it's it's you shouldn't see it
just like oh because this is a
requirement on that theoretical level
you should start feeling yourself the
peril of being still involved in the
central domain.
>> How does one do that? Say for example
they a person is not associating with
bad friends
uh is uh paying attention to their
environment in in the sense of like as
much as
um of an input as they have they're
exercising that so they're not
carelessly going into the sight sounds
melt touches unless they have to
minimizing exposure to that. you know
when the pressures um get too much
people still might be uh breaking the
presets even without the external
uh prompts and so on.
>> So
how would one train in that to not fail
there and to obviously
increase the the restraint without as you said
the the restraint without as you said
kind of slingshoting back.
So how would you those those values that
you talk about the danger that it's
dangerous for me engaging with it not
just kind of the secondary dangers and
warnings >> how can they directly um begin to see
>> how can they directly um begin to see
that?
Well, the first thing is
you might be tempted to um not want to
feel regret, not want to feel shame when
you do something unh wholesome and you
give into sensuality.
>> You might like that's exactly when
people resort to the views of oh well
you're a lay person. It's not a big
deal. >> It's not it's not
>> It's not it's not
>> absolved I'm absolved from
responsibility for this. It's not a
coincidence is because you don't want to
feel the the weight that comes when you
see oh I had this goal and I actually
walked against it.
>> Mhm.
>> So the first thing is like you will not
be able to properly develop that value
if
you don't want to feel ashamed because
that shame is the symptom of the value
being maintained. The shame is what
tells you like oh I'm actually
maintaining sight of what I should have
done. >> So
>> So
>> so not deny it. Exactly. So don't try to
to
uh push it away because as the Buddha
himself said uh fear of uh wrongdoing is
one of the basic faculties on the path
on the same level as mindfulness uh
samadei. So if you try to deny that
that's [clears throat] exactly how you
won't be you won't have that um you
won't be developing that internal
criteria that for example the sautapana
is what would be driving them to make
further progress like even if they might
as sometimes happen in the sutas um get
careless the fact is they wouldn't be
able to cover up that shame
>> that they know this is against the path
this is causing me harm taking me
because the harm the the the
danger of that whole thing that just
described >> has to be seen internally.
>> has to be seen internally.
>> So yeah, they wouldn't be able to cover
up the shame and consequently they would
not be able to develop uh further wrong
views that uh are used to make them cope
>> to make them justify to to kind of um u
well absolve them from the weight of
those actions.
Yeah, because covering up the shame,
you're covering up
the first kind of gateway to recognizing
the danger
>> or by not allowing it to come up, I
guess. Yeah.
>> By by saying, "Oh, this doesn't apply to
me. This requirement doesn't apply to
me." >> Because otherwise you just Yeah. You
>> Because otherwise you just Yeah. You
would feel too unpleasant,
>> right? Because Yeah. It's not that even
that you have to fabricate the shame.
>> You would see that it would be there on
its own just by maintaining the
perspective. This is the goal. Shame is
[clears throat] there automatically. if
you contradict it. So it's not even that
you have to work yourself up.
>> You abstain from wearing away the value
of withdrawal from sensuality. You will
feel shame whenever you
>> Okay. So if somebody's not denying the
shame, so they giving the precepts or
training in them, not associating with
bad friends,
um exercising their input as much as
they can in the suitable environment,
not denying shame when it arises. Is
there something more? Is there any other
things they can do? Well,
Well,
>> in terms of that danger, centrality,
values, >> you have to reflect on it frequently for
>> you have to reflect on it frequently for
sure.
>> Like,
>> give me some examples.
>> Um, well,
>> how would one reflect about it? As the
Buddha described, those um basic
reflections that everybody whether
layman or gone forth should cultivate.
>> Mhm.
>> That you're liable to things dear to you
being taken away. You're liable to
things not dear to you, to being exposed
to things not dear to you. You're liable
to whatever attachment you cultivate,
you will have to experience the pain of
that being taken.
>> It sounds like all those reflections are
have that like a personal threat to
them. >> So
>> So
any other example you could give of such
reflections that's not just phrases,
stock phrases from the sutas?
>> Yeah, you have to make it concrete. So,
do you have friends? Do you have family?
>> Do you have children?
>> Do you have a spouse? Do you have
possessions that you know make you wake
up in the morning and feel enthusiastic
about life?
>> So, you have to reflect in regard to
those being liable to destruction, not
just abstractly like, oh yeah, I will
lose what is dear to me.
>> But how will that reveal the danger of
essentiality? I mean, I might I might
reflect and say, "I'm going to lose this
in 10 days, but until then, I can enjoy
it." >> Well, but what's going to happen if you
>> Well, but what's going to happen if you
were cultivating the light for something
and then you lose it?
>> Well, but if I'm ready to lose it,
saying 10 days it's going away. I can't
stop it. Happened before, I'll be all
right, but I'll enjoy it in the
meantime. >> But if you're ready to lose it, then why
>> But if you're ready to lose it, then why
are you engaging in it now?
>> Well, because it provides pleasure.
Factual pleasure.
>> But that's
>> it's factually agreeable. So why would I
just waste nine days of enjoying it?
>> Well, that's the thing like if you if
you're honest with yourself, you'll see
presence of the light means
automatically liability to pain when
that thing is taken away. It's not a
matter of then [snorts] that the pain
will come right now just by on account
of having the light.
>> Mhm.
>> It's like hanging from a thread. You're
elevated hanging from a thread and when
that thread breaks you
>> Yeah. But until it breaks, I can enjoy
it. >> Yeah. But if you came down
>> Yeah. But if you came down
>> if the danger if the danger is when the
thing breaks or changes until then I'll
factually enjoy that happiness.
>> Well, no, the danger is that you're
hanging from a thread. So if instead of
trying to come down from that thread,
you keep enjoying what's up there or
keep enjoying the fruits at the top of
the tree.
>> Mhm.
>> As that Buddhist as the Buddhist said in
that simile,
>> then you can't be coming down at the
same time so that when the tree falls,
you won't suffer.
>> Mhm. So you like if you enjoy it, you're
postponing saving yourself
saving yourself
>> from the danger that's going to happen.
>> But again in the example I gave, it's
like in in plenty of instances um a
person is willing or able and the mind
is not necessarily even
uh upset or bother much by losing
certain things.
>> Mhm. which kind of then
almost like follows the conclusion
follows. So I can enjoy them until then
because I'm ready to give them up. So
why wouldn't I enjoy them? What's the
danger of that?
Well, but because often that's kind of
the point. It's like okay you know the
big attachments in this I can see the
danger of that but you know I don't see
any harm in uh tasting this touching
that the kind of I'm not attached to it
and factually like it's it's simply not
on that level of any attachment that
that you like oh I'll lose sleep over
this yet you still enjoy it and
according to sutas there's still danger
in those things
>> so where's the mistake there
>> so we're still saying sensual things not
just >> yeah yeah yeah sensual central of course
>> yeah yeah yeah sensual central of course
Well,
>> like sensuality in moderation. Think of
it like that. So, it's still central.
So, but but you you do you kind of
prevent yourself from getting too far
with it
>> because that would be like one of the
probably main things
>> practically speaking for people like you
know you might tell your environment,
set things up rightly,
>> but then there's going to be these
things that are obviously not on that
like a heavy level. um they are still
sensual and it's like there's absolutely
well nothing obviously dangerous about
it. >> So what what is that person missing?
>> So what what is that person missing?
>> Well, if you allow delight and pleasure
to the senses, you might be fine with
those specific sense objects being taken
away. >> But if you ask yourself honestly, will I
>> But if you ask yourself honestly, will I
will I be fine if I lose my sight? If I
go blind,
>> Mhm.
>> if I go deaf,
>> right?
>> Well, I'll be fine with that. And then
you realize, well, all of these things,
enjoying all these things implies taking
for granted, taking a safe that
situation of being healthy,
>> of being able to perceive these things.
>> Yeah. So basically, okay, so that's the
bigger picture they're missing out on.
Yeah. That's the connection
>> which is like you might factually be
able to handle a lot of engagement with
sensuality because you don't have
children, you don't have dependence, you
don't have burden that would have become
obvious through the years and so on. But
you do carry the burden of well being
intoxicated with your senses,
>> with your health, taking it for granted.
So every time you find joy in anything
sensual that's what the reflection needs to like
that's what the reflection needs to like
basically as we said you need to make it
personal. So how these impersonal sites
sounds melt touches that I can factually
handle if I engage with well how do I
make that personal as well
>> you can't make sites melt touches
personal >> because again they're irrelevant uh and
>> because again they're irrelevant uh and
more often than not. But what you can
then make personal is okay so what how
how would I engage with those objects
what is the necessary basis for any
engagement oh it's the senses it's the
sights it's the eyes which means the the
implicit taking for granted of that
basis is there and now you start seeing
oh but if that were to change if that
were to go away if that were to be lost
or get sick
>> I would not be indifferent even towards
these seemingly indifferent sites
touches >> so in other words if you think you can
>> so in other words if you think you can
handle sensuality.
Uh it's be to [clears throat] to the
extent you think you can handle it to
that extent you haven't taken it
personally enough
>> the bigger picture.
>> So that would be another contemplation
to to you know you could contemplate the
obvious as I said attachments and
dangers and things you fear things you
know you're anxious about
>> but then all these kind of um secondary
stuff that's not that's kind of almost
like neutral in and of itself but you
would still use it for enjoyment and the
pleasure. It's like well you got to also
now work through the same line of
reasoning and same level of reflection
to make that to include that into that
personal framework.
>> Yeah. Because if you think about it, you
could under some hypothetical
circumstance find a relatively safe set of external
find a relatively safe set of external
circumstances
>> that it's not like really super likely
to be taken away like a person who could
just die. Um but that doesn't mean that
you escaped the danger
>> cuz the tree that you're climbing on and
the fruits that you're enjoying are
fundamentally that level of your senses.
>> Yeah. So then the question is then how
to what would be the the practical
avenues of such reflections
of such reflections
>> like themes what themes
>> reflecting on death for example
>> reflecting on death.
>> So but yeah I guess that too could
become like an abstract just phrase that
you repeat. Yeah, that's the training.
It's like keep kind of as it becomes
abstract or dead, you have to make it
alive. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> No pun intended. Contemplation of death,
you have to make it alive.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, so any any other practical practical
ways? >> Well, you will have things that [snorts]
>> Well, you will have things that [snorts]
you particularly are afraid of.
>> So,
>> specific idiosyncratic little kind of
>> triggers, anxieties. So somebody may not
care too much about getting sick,
>> but they would very much resist the idea
of getting old,
>> for example.
>> So um so then the the training of this
reflection, it's really more like just
learning how to uncover and make these
connections. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Between the two because obviously well
the the most obvious example is when
somebody is healthy, they don't think
about illness.
Um, and they're absolutely convinced,
well, they'll handle they'll handle it
when it comes. Then when it comes, they
regret their behavior and how they got
sick in the first place. They wish they
never did it, but then they recover and
then they
>> intoxicated again. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, it's on the level of
intoxication.
>> Um, to this
uh getting to this point roughly,
someone could quite easily have just
removed uh the OB objects. M
uh the OB objects. M
>> whereas now it's like well how do I
remove my eyes
>> you know
>> my dependence so it's a
>> so obviously that's why we we've brought
up cont the idea of contemplation
reflection but there's quite a shift of
gears um in terms of how to go about
abandoning something
>> right because you might you might
maintain the momentum of like blaming
specific things
>> whereas um yeah of course it begins on
that level but you want to recognize
there there is just a a thread of things
being pleasant
>> that you will never be able to get rid
of. You will have to interact with
something >> sight, sound, smell, smell, taste, touch
>> sight, sound, smell, smell, taste, touch
that then could become essential for
you. >> So if you don't take it on that level of
>> So if you don't take it on that level of
my attitude towards the senses as as
tools to experience pleasure and and
move your restraint onto that level,
then you're just never going to
>> Well, yeah. I mean that's that's exactly
it would be like on the level of silabat
paramasa which is you know for for many
monks that's still the case even when
they live in the
>> a lot more suitable environment
>> they still would not and actually in a
ways in many ways without the right
instruction quote unquote suitable
environment would
>> could just uh
>> cover things up
>> well cover things up because it feels
like you did the work by adjusting to
the environment of restraint Right. But then
environment of restraint Right. But then
making zero effort to start reflecting
on and and and creating un uncovering
these connections
>> between because as I said like yeah you
might be oh I can handle this side
sounds touch but you actually do know
that you have anxieties and fears in
regard to certain things but you don't
see the connection. You don't see the
connection between
>> your delight your dependence on those
sense objects for pleasure. You don't
see the connection between that and the
existing basis for these anxieties, for
these fears, for these worries, for the
hindrances. >> And that will not be magically revealed
>> And that will not be magically revealed
by itself or some special method. You
have to be scraping that thing like
deeper and deeper and deeper until you
get to this like ah of course and then
the danger becomes apparent
>> like immediately seen verifiable. Each
time there is the light there is means
danger not like I have to work for the
connection. >> Yeah. Yeah, because [snorts] you might
>> Yeah. Yeah, because [snorts] you might
just associate these very specific
things. Okay, these are sensuality. And
then I've met people who who thought
factually thought that just by being
monks, >> they [snorts] were already withdrawn
>> they [snorts] were already withdrawn
from sensuality.
>> Failing to see that it's that
relationship with your senses,
>> not just, oh, I just changed this
environment and I'm already safe.
>> Yeah, it's what we said before. So it's
a a good criteria is to if you think if
you feel safe is to ask yourself you
know if you're a monk ask yourself if I
were to be forced to this robe now
>> and have the obvious external imperative
that my uniform suggests removed
imperative to to keep the precepts not
engage in sensuality be celibate would I
feel like uh be a able to go back to
those things
>> or would I feel like well nothing would
change doesn't matter what uniform I
fair internally
>> the the values remain completely aligned
and same as a householder like if if I
were to be forced to become a monk now
>> would I feel like at loss at at a at a
great peril and danger because I lost
the access to the possibility of
sensuality >> or would my mind remain unbothered by
>> or would my mind remain unbothered by
it?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. When that expectation of other
people holding you accountable and that
falls off,
>> then you know,
>> would you be able to hold yourself
accountable? >> Did I actually see the danger?
>> Did I actually see the danger?
>> Cuz you wouldn't need somebody to to be
watching you. So listen,
>> or if say somebody discovers now that
the sutas were actually written 300
years ago.
>> Yeah.
>> Some guy just sat and wrote them down
and the Buddha never existed.
>> Exactly.
>> And this was all just a fabrication. M
>> would you still see
>> would you still continue in the same
direction or would you say oh I don't
have to do any of this now?